[Music]
Welcome to this business central launch
event and this session about extending e
documents with new
interfaces. Today I will uh talk to you
about the technical updates for building
integrations with the e document
framework that are released in uh 2025
wave 1 also known as version 26.
This session is especially relevant to
you if uh you want to build a connector
and haven't done that yet with the e
document framework but also especially
if you have built a connector maybe even
released it
already then this session is really good
to watch. I also want to recommend
watching our previous BCLE sessions on
what's new in E documents that is for
release 2024 wave 1 and wave two because
those sessions are more in depth. Uh
they both cover the highle aspects but
also the technical bits in greater
detail than what we will do in today's
session. Today's session I will be uh
going mainly into the updates and what
you need to be aware of with the new
releases of these interfaces.
So without further ado, let's dive into
it. So the framework before this release
had uh one integration interface that
you would need uh to uh implement when
you build a connector. So this interface
had two main functions for sending and
receiving e documents and for approval
and cancellation actions for send e
documents. But why are we doing these
changes? Well, there were some
challenges in the existing model that we
first released. First of all, we didn't
have any uh proper error handling when
doing the receiving logic in the
framework. And that will mean that if
you for instance were trying to reach a
service that is currently unavailable,
we wouldn't uh be able to handle the
framework logic properly. Then we also
had some incomplete integration design
that we wanted uh to improve. Currently
in the old version it was patched with
some isandled events that we we uh yeah
we we dis like this approach and we
wanted to to get rid of uh for the e
document framework. And then of course
also from feedback uh that were partners
that we uh talked with that that told us
that there are lack of support for more
advanced uh connector scenarios and they
would like to see those improvements uh
for their connectors.
So from uh the last few months where
we've done a lot of partner
collaboration with the new connectors
we're shipping and the feedback through
uh Yammer and other sources, we decided
that okay this wave is a good good time
to to re-engineer this part of the
framework. So question what is it
actually that we we need to solve? Well,
first of all, we would like to protect
against if an integration service is
down, right? We want to remain in
control in the framework in the process.
We want to remain in control there and
not uh put the e document in a state uh
that is unexpected. And we also want to
make sure that if some somehow there are
some broken logic in the connector, then
we also want to take into account of
keeping the state in the in the
framework.
Um then of course we want to improve the
design and quality of these interfaces
now that we're changing them
specifically decrease the work that is
needed by an implementtor making it more
simple and then improving the
capabilities that these interfaces gives
gives connectors out of the box. Yeah.
And then of course uh we also want to
get rid of these uh patches of is
handled events that we had to add in uh
such that we also get get rid of these
uh problems with uh cross implementation
where if one bad connector gets
installed that doesn't handle these
events properly it affects all the
connectors and so on. So the solution or
the answer to that is essentially what
is new in in this release because we are
providing now five new interfaces and
don't worry it's uh it is not meant to
scare you that there are five because
four of them uh the first four is what
is the equivalent to the old e document
integration in terms of uh capabilities
they just improved and then they're
separated to make each interface more
simple to work with and also separate
the concerns in the when building the
application making it simpler for the
developer. So this is an improved API
design with simplified logic both in the
framework but also in in the connectors.
And then we added this I document action
interface as a way of standardizing
document actions. And what do I mean by
that? Well, some connectors might want
to do specific calls to their service,
do specific actions. Um and we want to
give you that opportunity without having
to deal with state management in the e
document framework. So we provide this
interface where you can implement a
custom action just focus on the logic
for sending to your service and passing
the response and then we will deal with
updating the document and all the state
accordingly. This is of course already
updated in our uh current connectors.
Aggerero and Avalara is updated and the
new ones logic and signup that we're
shipping in in this release have also
been using these new interfaces. So that
we've already had them through partners
that have worked with them and gotten
feedback which is really
good. So let's dive into a little bit in
a little bit more detail how this looks
so you really get an understanding of
the difference between version 25 and
version 26. So in version 25 we had the
e document integration interface that
your code unit would implement. In the
new version for sending specifically you
implement the I document
sender and the I document sender has the
same parameters as before with the
exception of the send context code unit
that is now provided as the third
parameter and this one is just a wrapper
for the HTTP response and request
information as well as any data that you
want to send. And as we can see here in
the example from Avalara I have with me
today. We are reading out the templ from
the send context that is provided by the
framework in my uh implementation. Then
I'm sending it off to Avalara getting
back the response and storing that
document ID that they assigned me. Then
we have sending with asynchronous
responses. Beforehand in the old version
again in the the E document integration
interface this was a a parameter a sync
um now instead we've changed it to be a
new interface that you can optionally
implement it's called I document
response handler and if you implement
this one for your solution then you will
be using a synchronous uh communication
and what specifically do I mean with
asynchronous in this case just to remind
you it is when you send a a document to
a service and then they are going to
process that document verify that the
contents are okay. Then you said send
another request to ask basically
verify what I send is it
okay and as you can see here it is the
get response method that you will be
implementing. It has the same parameters
as the send and uh the the example for
my hour is quite straightforward. I just
create a request. I send it off and then
I I exit the the boolean true or false.
True if it is actually processed by the
server and it's okay or false if they're
still uh continuing to process or
throwing an error in case that that the
server comes back and says that there is
an error in the document you sent such
that we can handle that in the framework
accordingly.
So sending is very similar to what it
was before. We have bigger changes in
receiving. Still they're quite simple to
to migrate, but these is these changes
are uh bigger. So in version 25, we had
the receive document and get document
count in batch as functions in the
interface. And then we had to throw in
this is handled event called on after
insert imported document for you to go
fetch the XML from from the server and
attach it to the the E document. And
this was not exactly what we wanted or
it was something that was the first
version at least and now in the in the
new version we have this only handled by
by the interface. So we have two
functions that you will implement in the
eye document receiver. One of them is
called receive documents and the other
one is called download document and
there is no need for for is handled
events
here to see how it looks. Let's start
with the receive documents. So in I
document receiver you get the service
that you want to receive for then a
templ. So that is a list that you need
to fill out with the documents that you
get from the service that you are to
receive. And these will contain metadata
about the documents. And then a receive
context the variable which is the same
as before HTTP response and request. And
the the data templ is stored in this uh
uh receive context. And as you can see
from the Avalara example here, we are
getting a response with new documents
and then we're iterating over them and
we are inserting uh the metadata for
each one of them into this
templ then ensure to create new e
documents for each of these metadata
objects and that looks like this. So the
download document procedure will be
called for each one of these and it will
have the single templ with the document
metadata related to this specific e
document. And the task as you can see
here in the example is then to take that
metadata and go fetch the actual
contents of the E document. So that is
the XML. That is what we're doing here.
And we're then storing that in the
templ. And that is passed back to the
framework. And voila, then you have a e
document inside business
central. Then we have added a new uh new
feature or a new or enriched the
capabilities of the interfaces with I
received document
marker. This one is to acknowledge that
you received something. Some services
allow you to send a request saying I
received this document so don't send it
to me again. essentially uh and this is
if you again implement this interface
it's optional then you have the ability
to to turn that on in your connector and
tell the service that you had received a
document so essentially your code unit
can choose to implement it or not
depending on your use
case so the key benefits of this is of
course the improved API design and this
separation of concerns where we have
smaller pieces of interfaces is that
each deal with different uh smaller
problems. It is a it simplifies the
logic both in the connectors but also
for us in the framework. It is also safe
because now we actually catch errors
when HTTP communication fails on the
receiving side. So then we can continue
the the receiving process um as we
intended to do. It is all explicit
implementation. there are no event uh
subscribers essentially allowing for for
multiple connectors to being installed
without this worry of one connector
doing a a bad job of its implementation
and affecting the rest. We've seen that
and that is feedback we've gotten. Um so
it's good to see that this improvement
will get rid of
it. Yeah. And then also with some of the
new interfaces, you can build more
advanced connectors. And then the the
final thing, the standardized document
actions. Again, focus on writing the
logic for sending the request and
passing it back and let the framework
handle all the state updates. You just
give it the necessary information and
our uh framework will will then take
care of that and make sure that it's the
same user experience across connectors.
So what are the next steps for you?
Right? So now we have these new
interfaces. They're available from this
release. The old interfaces are
deprecated and will be removed in three
waves. So that is 2026 wave
2. Migration to the new ones is simple
luckily and uh you can follow the new
and improved documentation we've made
available on Microsoft learn. Just
follow the link here in the um you can
find it on Microsoft learn. It's called
extending uh the e documents
functionality. Another advice I think
you should take with you is also to use
the existing connectors to help you
build your own because now we have four
examples and more to come. They are all
available on AL app extensions and you
can find them under e document
connectors and then they will be folder
based for each of them. And here you can
go and take inspiration and see how
different connectors uh does it. And
that is essentially everything for me in
this session about the new and improved
interfaces. Thank you for watching.